[Music]
start with a real number a between minus
one and one
to compute the integral of the square
root of one minus x squared between a
and one using the fundamental theorem of
calculus you need a trig substitution
and some trig identities however we can
also remember that this integral
represents the area under the square
root of one minus x squared between x
equals a
and x equals one like this to find this
area we can first find the area of the
full sector covering the region
if this sector has angle alpha then the
area is one half alpha because the
radius is one
the area we want is this area minus the
area of this right triangle
with base a and height square root of
one minus a squared
note that this right triangle also shows
that the cosine of alpha
is a so that alpha is the arc cosine
of a giving the formula for the area we
want in terms of a
but this diagram only works if a is
positive
if a is negative the region that we want
looks a little something like this
luckily this region is now the union of
a sector in a right triangle
again if this sector has angle alpha
then the area
is one-half alpha
this time we add the area of the
triangle
which now has base negative a and height
square root of 1 minus a
squared as before alpha
is the arc cosine of a
and we can think of adding the negative
as subtracting
this yields the same formula as before
so in either of these two cases the
integral that we want
is given by the arc cosine of a over two
minus one half a times the square root
of one minus a squared
you